Guide to the Eugene J. Webb Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Eugene J. Webb papers
1961-1994
SC0504
Webb, Eugene J., 1933-1995
8.5 Linear feet
Professional papers relating to courses Webb taught at the Graduate School of Business at Stanford University and his research interests such as philanthropy, altruism, effect of deadlines on human behavior, and organizational behavior. Included are correspondence, notebooks, articles, subject files, course materials, papers by students, case studies, and articles by others. Correspondents include Robert B. Cialdini, Morris E. Eson, Claude Faucheux, John W. Gardner, Steven Jobs, Jeffrey Pfeffer, and Jon Van Til. There are also materials from an executive education program for corporate board directors that Webb developed.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Eugene J. Webb, a pioneer in the development of research and teaching of organizational behavior in business schools, joined the faculty of the Graduate School of Business at Stanford in 1968. He earned his A.B. at SUNY Albany in 1954 and his Ph.D. at the University of Chicago in 1956; he worked in the advertising industry and then taught at Northwestern University prior to his arrival at Stanford.
At Stanford he was the founding director of the Public Management Program, created and taught many innovative courses, and developed an executive education program for corporate board directors. In addition to his teaching duties, Webb was an associate dean of the Graduate School of Business and served as chairman of the university's Faculty Senate. In 1977 he became the first holder of the Lane Family Professorship in the Business School.
Webb's best known book was Unobstrusive Measures: Nonreactive Research in the Social Sciences. His research interests included philanthropy, altruism, and the effect of deadlines on human behavior.
Webb died in March of 1995.
Description of the Collection
The papers of Eugene J. Webb are largely his professional papers pertaining to his teaching activities in the Graduate School of Business at Stanford and his research interests. Included are correspondence, course materials, notebooks, papers and articles, case studies, subject files, students' papers, and articles by others.
These papers had no particular order when received. In processing them, they were arranged in the following manner: correspondence, course materials, writings by Webb, subject files, and source materials.
Access Terms
Bing, Peter S.; Cannon, Warren M.; Cialdini, Robert B.; Eson, Morris E.; Faucheux, Claude.; Gardner, John W. (John William), 1912-2002; Guthrie, James W.; Kirst, Michael W.; Leavitt, Harold J.; Makridakis, Spyros G.; Miller, Arjay R.; Patell, James M.; Pfeffer, Jeffrey.; Pond, Samuel A.; Porterfield, James T.S.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Business. Curricula.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Business; Van Til, Jon.; Webb, Eugene J., 1933-1995; Weingast, Barry R.; Altruism.; business; Business education --United States.; Charities; Organizational behavior.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Sobrovin, Alexei - correspondence and papers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (from Webb), no date (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence A-F (to Webb), 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence G-P (to Webb), 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Q-T (to Webb), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence T-Z (to Webb), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (to Webb) incomplete or unclear, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Business 270: History !Evolution in Business, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Business 378: Course Materials, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Business 470 Materials #1 (from Binder), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Business 470 Materials #2 (from binder) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Business 470 Materials #3 (from binder) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Business 470 materials #4 (from binder) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Business 470 materials #5 (from binder), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Business 470 Materials #6 (from binder) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Business 470 Materials #7 (from binder) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Business 470 Materials #8 (from binder) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Business 470 Materials #9 (from binder) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Business 470 Materials #11 (from binder) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Business 470 Materials #11 (from binder) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Business 470 Materials #12 (from binder) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Business 470 Materials #13 (from binder) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Business 474: Topics in Philanthropy, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Business 474: Topics in Philanthropy, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Business 474/3:, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Business 474: Philanthropy, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#1 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#2 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#3 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#4 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#5 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#5 materials) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Business 477 Binder #1 (#5 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#1 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#2 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#3 materials), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#4 materials), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#5 materials) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#6 materials) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#7 materials), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#8 materials), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#9 materials), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Business 477 Binder #2 (#10 materials), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Business 570/ Case Studies, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Business 601: References (Altruism)(Thwarting Predators) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Student Paper - fragments (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Course Materials - Miscellaneous, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Overhead Slides (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors Program, Binder #1, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Program, Binder #2, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Program, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Apple Computer Company, 1983 - 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Girl Scouts, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Netsuki Case Study (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - O'Melveny and MyerslNFL Case, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Time Wamer Case, 1986 -1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Time Warner Case #2, 1986 -1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Walsh System, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Case Studies, 1972 -1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Case Studies - Miscellaneous, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Papers by Webb: Advertising, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Papers by Webb: Allocation, (late 1960s?) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Papers by Webb: Altruism, 1983, 1988, 1991, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Papers by Webb: Implementing, 1983, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Papers by Webb: Media, 1961, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Papers by Webb: Methodology, 1969-1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Papers by Webb: Nature and Knowing, 1966-1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Papers By Webb: Predicting, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Papers by Webb: Social Science, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Notebooks, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Memos / Miscellaneous notes, 1963-1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Articles with Annotations, 1975-1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Altruism Paper, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Altruisrn/PhilanthropylBiological vs. Social Evolution, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Altruisrn/Philanthropy Topics, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Altruisrn/Philanthropy (Miscellaneous), 1984-1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Altruism and Philanthropy-Research Paper 1104, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Altruism-Research Paper 1104-Role of Religion ..., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Altruism notes/miscellaneous, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bryan Borys Proposal, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Business History (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Charitable Giving... (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Charitable Giving (overhead projector slides) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Community Foundations (of Santa Clara County), 1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Compendium of Resources ... Philanthropy (from binder), 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Notes from binder of "Compendium of Resources", 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Confederacies Study, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Conflict: Fight-Flight (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Cooperation/ Partnerships in Giving, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Corporate Culture (Changing), 1988 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Corporate Philanthropy, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Deadlines Project (from binder (#1)), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Deadlines Project (from binder (#2)), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Deadlines Project (from binder (#3)), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Deadlines Project (from binder (#4)), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Deadlines Study, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Demography, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Dissent Group Process ... (13 days), 1984 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Dupont Seminar 8/88, August, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Equity (theory; between people), 1984, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - The Experience Corps, 1991-1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - F.I.T.-Families in Transition, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - F.I.T.-Families in Transition, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Families in Transition- Fundraising Letters, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Families in Transition (3/9/89), 1989 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Families in Transition: Direct Mail, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Families in Transition (notes), 1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Federalism, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Fund Raising Tactics Project, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Fund Raising Tactics, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Greece 1991 (Athens Laboratory of Business Administration), 1991, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Implementation as Metaphor (paper), 1982 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Indirect Methods in Attitude Research (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - INSEAD, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - John Gardner Fellowships, 1988-1994 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Las Vegas 94, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Law and Society Review, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Law: Weighted Caseload System, 1982, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Limits of Rationality, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Motivating Donors, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Non Profit Journal, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - O.B. ACE (group assessment) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Obedience (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Official Business, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Offshoot (Market Penetration by Outside Industry), 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - O.O.F. (Organizations of the Future), 1970 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Oral History File, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Organization Intelligence, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Organization Life and Death, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - PACE: Policy Analysis for California Education, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Palm Drive, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Parallels between Philanthropy and Finance Theory, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Philanthropy Binder (#1), 1991 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Philanthropy Binder (#2), 1991 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Philanthropy Binder (#3), 1988 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Philanthropy Binder (#4), 1979 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Philanthropy Binder (#5) (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Power and Politics in Organizations, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Power Table (Control, Power, and Influence), 1990 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Protest Absorption, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Reagan-Bush Commercials, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Reducing Effort in Giving, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Regret Matrix (Formal Model), 1994 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - SCC (Senior Coordinating Council-Palo Alto), 1984, 1985, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Starwars Defense Initiative (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Self Esteem (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Stability Change (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Standards for Charities/Watchdogs, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Steady State Group (study), 1973, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Stockholm Connection, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Thailand Management, 1982-1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Thorson Memorial Fellowship (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Timing Study, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Tom Peters Group-Europe, June, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Urban Management: Periodicityrriming, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Volunteers, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Volunteering, 1991, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Work Values, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Sources: Artic1es/Papers (alphabetical by author) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Sources: Newspaper Clippings (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Sources: Giving USA Update, 1990-1993 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Sources: Circulars/Pamplets (Box 15, Folder 4)
General note
Personal Name Index
Allen, Peter C. 12 9 Letters
Arkwright, Marianne 10 7
Arrillaga, Fran 10 2
Arvedson, Lennart 9 3
Arvedson, Lennart 13 7 Letters
Atieh, Jennifer M. 14 8
Baier, Vicki Eaton 11 6
Bandura, Albert 13 3
Baron, J. 13 7 Letters
Bennis, Warren 11 2
Bies, Robert J. 10 1
Bing, Peter S. 1 10 Letters
Blanchett, Herbert A. 12 9 Letters
Brief, Arthur P. 14 8
Bundhurat, Jakravudh 14 1 Letters
Burgelman 13 7 Letters
Campbell, Donald T. 6 6
Campbell, Donald T. 6 9
Campbell, Donald T. 7 2
Cannon, Warren 13 6 Letters
Carpenter, Guy 1 14 Letters
Chaiseri, Nongyao 14 1 Letters
Chesney, Maxine Mackler 11 12
Cialdini, Robert B. 10 5
Cialdini, Robert B. 1 10 Letters
Davis-Blake, Alison 1 10 Letters
Davis-Blake, Alison 10 1
de Bettignies, Henri-Claude 1 10 Letters
Dean, John Gunther 14 1 Letters
Dietel, William M. 1 10 Letters
Doherty, Elizabeth M. 14 8
Dowling, John B. 9 3
Dowling, John B. 9 4
Dowling, John B. 9 5
Efthymiou, George 11 5 Letters
Ellsworth, Phoebe C. 6 7
Ely, Lenard 10 2
Embeoglou, N. M. 11 5 Letters
Esariya-umpai, Radaporn 14 1 Letters
Eson, Morris E. 1 10 Letters
Eson, Morris E. 6 3
Eson, Morris E. 7 1
Eson, Morris E. 7 3
Eson, Morris E. 7 5
Eson, Morris E. 10 1
Faucheux, Claude 1 10 Letters
Freitas, Joseph 11 12
Gardner, John W. 1 11 Letters
Grauer, Frederick L.A. 9 2
Grauer, Frederick L.A. 9 5
Gump, Patricia 1 11 Letters
Guthrie, James W. 12 12 Letters
Gwynn, Kathi 10 2
Handy, Charles 11 2
Hannan, Michael 11 12
Harrell, Tom Willard 1 11 Letters
Heyns, Roger 10 5
Howell, James Edwin 1 11
Israsena, Paron 14 1 Letters
Jerrell, Lee 9 3
Jobs, Steven P. 1 11 Letters
Kennedy, Judy 11 1
Kirst, Michael W. 12 12 Letters
Koziol, Ken 1 11 Letters
Leavitt, Harold J. 6 4
Leavitt, Harold J. 6 9
Leavitt, Harold J. 12 1
Leavitt, Harold J. 13 6 Letters
Lodato, Frank 10 2
Lund, Mary 10 7
Lurvey, Ira 11 12
Makridakis, Spyros 11 5 Letters
March, James G. 11 6
Martin, Myron 11 12
McClelland, Kathy 10 5
McClelland, Kathy 11 1
McMillan, Brockway 13 2
Miller, Arjay R. 12 9 Letters
Mitchell, James 10 1
Morison, Robert 12 11
Munoz, Frances 11 12
Nemeth, Charlan Jeanne 9 7
Nichols, William F. 10 5
Nord, Walter R. 14 8
Okamura, Edwin A. 1 11 Letters
O'Keefe, Brian 1 11 Letters
Olanvoravuth, Ninnat 14 1 Letters
O'Toole, James 11 2
Patell, James M. 1 11 Letters
Patell, James M. 1 11 Letters
Peters, Thomas J. 6 4
Peters, Thomas J. 11 6
Pfeffer, Jeffrey 9 6
Pfeffer, Jeffrey 10 1
Pfeffer, Jeffrey 11 12
Pfeffer, Jeffrey 12 20
Pfeffer, Jeffrey 13 7 Letters
Pond, Pete 12 9 Letters
Pond, Samuel A. 13 6 Letters
Porras, Jerry I. 11 12
Porterfield, James T.S. 1 11 Letters
Raisian, John 10 1
Robinson, Norm 10 2
Saetren, Harald 11 6
Salancik, Gerald R. 6 5
Salancik, Gerald R. 6 6
Salancik, Gerald R. 11 7
Salancik, Gerald R. 12 20
Schauer, Richard 11 12
Scott, Sandy 10 2
Shapiro, Debra L. 10 1
Sherman, Daniel J. 1 12 Letters
Shuel, Ted B. 10 7 Letters
Simon, Robert W. 13 6 Letters
Smith, Hedrick 13 2
Sobrovin, Alexei 1 1 Letters
Somerville, Bill 10 5
Somerville, Bill 12 2 Letters
Sommer, Robert 1 12
Spero, Robert 10 7
Srisupandit, Somburana 14 1
Troxell, John 1 12 Letters
Van Til, Jon 6 3
Van Til, Jon 12 3 Letters
Ward, Michael P. 10 1
Watzke, Gerard E. 6 8
Weick, Karl E. 6 6
Weiner, Stephen S. 9 3
Weingast, Barry R. 1 13 Letters
Welch, Finis 10 1
Wilson, Liz 1 13 Letters
Wright, Peter 11 1